So far in this lesson, you've been doing computations on
在这节课中 到目前为止
series using built-in functions.
你始终在 Series 上使用内置函数进行计算
For example, the mean function and vectorized operations.
例如 平均值函数和向量运算
For example, plus for vectorized addition.
比如 代表向量加法的加号
But what do you do when you want to perform some
但如果你要进行的计算
calculation that's not built into pandas and
在 Pandas 中没有内置函数
can't be performed using simple vector s operations?
也无法通过简单的向量运算进行 那怎么办？
Like you saw before,
与之前一样
one option would be to treat the series as a list using
可以将 Series 视为列表
four loops or
利用 for 循环
accessing individual elements of thee series.
或者 获取 Series 的单个元素
There is another option though,
还有另外一种方法
pandas has a function called apply(), which you can use to
Pandas 有一个名为 apply 的函数
perform computations that aren't built into Pandas.
你可以用它进行 Pandas 中没有内置的计算
Apply() takes a series and
apply 函数会载入 Series 和函数
a function and it creates a new series by applying
然后 通过对原 Series 的每个元素调用 (apply) 这个函数
the function to every element of the original series.
创建一个新的 Series
So for example, suppose the function was add three,
比如 假设把函数与 3 相加
which takes a number and adds three to it.
也就是把数字与 3 相加
Applying this function to the series on the left would give
对左侧 Series 调用该函数
the series on the right.
就会得到右侧的 Series
First, add three would be applied to the first element
首先 Series 的第一个元素与 3 相加
of the series giving four.
会得到 4
Then add three would be applied to the second element
然后 再把 Series 的第二个元素与 3
of the series, giving five.
相加得到 5
Then to the third element of the series, giving six and
然后 再把 Series 的第三个元素与 3 相加
so on.
得到 6 以此类推
If you're familiar with the Python function map apply() is
如果你熟悉 Python 的 map apply 函数
exactly the same, but it works on series instead of lists.
两者其实是一样的 只不过这个在 Series 而不是列表上运行
If you haven't heard of map, that's okay too.
如果你没有听说过 map apply 函数 也没关系
Now in this example of adding three,
在这个加 3 的例子中
it would have been better to use vectorized addition.
使用向量加法会更好
If this series were named s,
如果这个 Series 叫做 s
then you could create the new series with the code s+3.
那么你就可以用代码 s + 3 创建新的 Series
And this would do the same thing as s.apply(add 3).
这与 s.apply(add3) 是一样的
However, apply() can be very useful in cases where there is
但在没有你需要的内置运算时
no built-in operation that does what you want.
apply 函数就很有用了
For example, suppose you have a series of states where some
例如 假如你有一个州的 Series
states are represented by the full name and
其中 部分州是全称
others by the abbreviation.
其它的是简称
I want to clean up the data by replacing each full state by
我想要清理数据
its abbreviation.
用各州的简称代替其全称
Now let's say,
假设
I've already written a function that does this for
我已经编写了
a single state.
清理单个数据的函数
The code might look something like this.
这个代码大概就是这样的
First, I check if the value is already an abbreviation.
首先 我检查这个值是否是简称
In which case, I return it unchanged.
如果是 我不做改动 直接返回
Next, I check if the state is Alabama.
接下来 我检查这个州是否是阿拉巴马
In which case, I return the abbreviation for Alabama, and
如果是 我就返回阿拉巴马的简称
so on, you get the idea.
以此类推
Now I could create an empty list,
我可以创建一个空列表
then loop over the series, then call my clean_state
遍历这个 Series
function on each value in the series and
然后 对 Series 中的每个元素调用我的 clean_state 函数
append each new value to the list.
再将每个新值添加到列表中
But I probably really wanted my cleaned data to be a panda
但我希望清理后的数据是 Panda Series
series rather than a list, so
而不是列表
I could convert this list to a series at the end of the loop.
所以 我可以在循环末尾将列表转换为 Series
Instead though, I could use the apply() function.
我也可以利用 apply 函数
First, I type the name of my original series,
首先 我写出原 Series 的名称
which is states, then I call the apply function.
也就是州名称 然后 我调用 apply 函数
And as an argument to the apply() function,
并把我用来清理州数据的
I give the clean_state function that I wrote to clean
clean_state 函数
up each state.
作为 apply 函数的参数
Note that I don't put parenthesis after
注意 我并没有在 clean_state 函数后面加小括号
the clean_state function, I'm not calling the function here.
在这里 我不是调用这个函数
I'm giving the entire function as an input to apply().
我是将整个函数作为 apply 函数的参数
The main advantage of using apply() over a loop is that it
与循环相比 使用 apply 函数的优点在于
makes your code a lot more concise.
它能使你的代码更简洁
It might also be slightly faster.
它的运算速度也会快一些
But in this case, the bulk of the time will probably be
但在这里 大部分时间可能会
spent within the clean_state function.
花在 clean_state 函数内
So, it probably won´t matter much from a speed
所以 就速度而言
perspective whether I use a loop or apply().
使用 loop (循环) 或 apply 函数可能没什么区别
Now, it's your turn.
现在轮到你来做了
Write code that will take a series of names in the form
你需要编写一个函数
of, firstname, lastname and
使其载入格式为名和姓的名字 Series
then put them into the form lastname, firstname.
然后 将其转换为姓和名的格式
You might find Python's split function helpful, there's
Python 的 split 函数可能比较有用
a link to documentation in the instructor notes.
讲师注释中有相关文件的链接